[
  {
    "question": "Which Indian institute developed a self-actuating drug delivery system for rheumatoid arthritis treatment?",
    "options": [
      "AIIMS Delhi",
      "INST Mohali",
      "IIT Bombay",
      "CSIR-CCMB",
      "IIM Ahmedabad"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the lead researcher heading the 40-day global expedition in the Ross Sea, a marine protected zone in Antarctica, to assess marine biodiversity, study environmental DNA, and analyze the region's impact on global ocean currents and climate change?",
    "options": [
      "Madhavan Rajeevan",
      "M. Ravichandran",
      "Sherine Sonia Cubelio",
      "Anil Bhardwaj",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which institution launched India's first Cancer Genome Atlas (BCGA) for early breast cancer detection?",
    "options": [
      "AIIMS Delhi",
      "Tata Memorial Hospital",
      "NIMHANS",
      "IIT Madras",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which team did Uttar Pradesh Men's Kabaddi Team defeat 57-43 to win the gold medal?",
    "options": [
      "Haryana",
      "Chandigarh",
      "Maharashtra",
      "Punjab",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which team won the inaugural World Pickleball League (WPL) championship, defeating Pune United 3-1 in the final?",
    "options": [
      "Bengaluru Jawans",
      "Pune United",
      "Mumbai Mavericks",
      "Delhi Warriors",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Bengaluru Jawans"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which architect was recognized as the Best Architect for Luxury Project at the Global Architect Builder Awards 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Dishna Thilanka",
      "Arun Kumar",
      "Hiten Patel",
      "Vivek Singh Rao",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country topped the Global Digital Well-Being Index with the highest score in online safety and parental support?",
    "options": [
      "United States",
      "India",
      "Australia",
      "United Kingdom",
      "Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organization released the redefined and augmented Research Verticals & Thrust Areas to enhance research focus in defense technology?",
    "options": [
      "Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)",
      "Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO)",
      "National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)",
      "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which veteran British actor, known for his role as George Roper in Man About the House and George & Mildred, passed away at the age of 92?",
    "options": [
      "John Cleese",
      "Brian Murphy",
      "David Jason",
      "Ronnie Barker",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the recently launched scheme designed to enhance agricultural productivity, promote crop diversification, and strengthen post-harvest storage at panchayat and block levels?",
    "options": [
      "PM Kisan Samman Nidhi Yojana",
      "PM Krishi Vikas Yojana",
      "PM Fasal Bima Yojana",
      "PM Dhan Dhanya Krishi Yojana",
      "PM SVANIDHI"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region has been projected by the WHO to witness an 85% increase in cancer cases and deaths by 2050?",
    "options": [
      "Africa",
      "Europe",
      "North America",
      "South-East Asia",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where will India open a new Consulate during PM Modi's visit to France in February 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Nice",
      "Marseille",
      "Lyon",
      "Toulouse",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which university's researchers discovered the new phytopathogenic fungus Epicoccum indicum, associated with an emerging leaf spot disease in Chrysopogon zizanioides (vetiver)?",
    "options": [
      "Punjab University",
      "Banaras Hindu University",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru University",
      "University of Hyderabad",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which payment system remains the major driver of digital payments in India as per the recent report February 2025?",
    "options": [
      "IMPS",
      "NEFT",
      "UPI",
      "All of the above",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "UPI"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who from Rajasthan has been shortlisted for the USD 1 million GEMS Education Global Teacher Prize 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Mohammad Imran Khan Mewati",
      "Dr. Ramesh Kumar",
      "Shalini Gupta",
      "Rajesh Kumar",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Mohammad Imran Khan Mewati"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who won the Tata Steel Masters Chess Tournament 2025 by defeating D Gukesh in the tiebreaker?",
    "options": [
      "Vincent Keymer",
      "R Praggnanandhaa",
      "Arjun Erigaisi",
      "Wei Yi",
      "Magnus Carlsen"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who became the first Black woman to win the Mrs World title in the competition's 40-year history?",
    "options": [
      "Tshego Gaelae",
      "Relebogile Mabotja",
      "Zozibini Tunzi",
      "Shudu Musida",
      "Rabia Fateh"
    ],
    "answer": "Tshego Gaelae"
  },
  {
    "question": "By what percentage has India's fruit and vegetable exports increased in the last five years, as per the Ministry of Commerce and Industry?",
    "options": [
      "35.8%",
      "50.1%",
      "47.3%",
      "41.5%",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the world's largest iceberg that is set to strike South Georgia Island?",
    "options": [
      "Iceberg B15",
      "Iceberg A23a",
      "Iceberg C19",
      "Iceberg D16",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which state has been allocated â‚¹23,778 crore for railway projects in the Budget 2025-26?",
    "options": [
      "Bihar",
      "Uttar Pradesh",
      "Maharashtra",
      "Lucknow",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the full form of VSHORAD in the context of DRDO's missile system?",
    "options": [
      "Very Small High-Output Radar Air Defence",
      "Very Short-Range Air Defence",
      "Variable Spectrum High-Range Air Defence",
      "Vertical Strike Hypersonic Operational Radar Air Defence",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Recently, Marcus Stoinis has announced his retirement from ODIs, ending a 74-match career. Which country does he hail from?",
    "options": [
      "South Africa",
      "England",
      "Australia",
      "New Zealand",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Indian research institute developed the novel high-entropy alloy (HEA) catalyst for green hydrogen production?",
    "options": [
      "Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Madras",
      "Indian Institute of Science (IISc)",
      "Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC)",
      "Centre for Nano and Soft Matter Sciences (CeNS)",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where in West Asia is the Medlab Middle East 2025 exhibition being held?",
    "options": [
      "Riyadh, Saudi Arabia",
      "Dubai, UAE",
      "Doha, Qatar",
      "Khartoum, Sudan",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the Indian-origin artist who won the Grammy Award for Best New Age, Ambient, or Chant Album in 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Ricky Kej",
      "Anoushka Shankar",
      "Chandrika Tandon",
      "Radhika Vekaria",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the new radio series launched by Akashvani on Basant Panchami to promote Indian classical music?",
    "options": [
      "Swar Bharat",
      "Raag Sarita",
      "Sangeet Mala",
      "Har Kanthh Mein Bharat",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Recently SCO Secretary General holds talks with MEA Secretary, Who is the current Secretary-General of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO)?",
    "options": [
      "Zhang Ming",
      "Nurlan Yermekbayev",
      "Sergey Lavrov",
      "Wang Yi",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is organizing WAVES 2025, which will introduce AI solutions for live misinformation detection?",
    "options": [
      "NITI Aayog and MeitY",
      "IT Ministry and ICEA",
      "RBI and Digital India Corporation",
      "Ministry of Home Affairs and NIC",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following states has contributed significantly to India's total utility-scale solar installations as per the recent achievement of 100 GW solar power capacity?",
    "options": [
      "Rajasthan, Gujarat, Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra, and Madhya Pradesh",
      "Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Chhattisgarh, Odisha, and Assam",
      "Kerala, Karnataka, Punjab, Haryana, and West Bengal",
      "Bihar, Jharkhand, Uttar Pradesh, Uttarakhand, and Himachal Pradesh",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Rajasthan, Gujarat, Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra, and Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where was the National Institute of Electronics and Information Technology (NIELIT) Centre of Excellence in Chip Design inaugurated which is aimed to bolster India's VLSI & semiconductor capabilities?",
    "options": [
      "Bengaluru",
      "Hyderabad",
      "Noida",
      "Chennai",
      "Mumbai"
    ],
    "answer": "Noida"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country has decided to end aid programs for Bangladesh, Albania, and Zambia due to a reduced foreign aid budget?",
    "options": [
      "Germany",
      "Switzerland",
      "France",
      "Sweden",
      "Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which South-East Asian country declared a food security emergency to curb soaring rice prices in 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Vietnam",
      "Thailand",
      "Indonesia",
      "Philippines",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the theme of World Wetlands Day 2025 celebrated at Parvati Arga Ramsar Site in Gonda, Uttar Pradesh?",
    "options": [
      "Wetlands and Water",
      "Protecting Wetlands for our Common Future",
      "Wetlands and Biodiversity",
      "Sustainable Wetlands for a Better Tomorrow",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the venue for the 9th Asian Winter Games 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Seoul, South Korea",
      "Quezon City, Philippines",
      "Harbin, China",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Recently government has said 864 km of India-Bangladesh border yet to be fenced in loksabha, Which force is responsible for guarding the India-Bangladesh border?",
    "options": [
      "Assam Rifles",
      "Border Security Force (BSF)",
      "Indo-Tibetan Border Police (ITBP)",
      "National Security Guard (NSG)",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "How much did India contribute to the United Nations Regular Budget for the year 2025?",
    "options": [
      "$25.34 million",
      "$37.64 million",
      "$40.12 million",
      "$50.91 million",
      "$66.91 million"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country became the first in Africa to eliminate onchocerciasis (river blindness) as a public health problem?",
    "options": [
      "Niger",
      "Kenya",
      "South Africa",
      "Democratic Republic of Congo",
      "Eritrea"
    ],
    "answer": "Niger"
  },
  {
    "question": "Former world number one and two-time Grand Slam winner Simona Halep announced her retirement from professional tennis in February 2025. Which country does she hail from?",
    "options": [
      "Albania",
      "Croatia",
      "Romania",
      "Germany",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Romania"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which project led to the creation of a new map of the Arctic Ocean, revealing an area twice the size of France and six times the size of England?",
    "options": [
      "Ocean Discovery 2050",
      "Seabed 2030",
      "Arctic Exploration Initiative",
      "Deep Sea Mapping Project",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country announced a 25% retaliatory tariff on American imports in response to U.S. trade policies?",
    "options": [
      "China",
      "Canada",
      "Mexico",
      "Germany",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Recently, Digi Yatra app user base has crossed 10 million+ with 30,000 daily downloads. The app was launched in which year?",
    "options": [
      "2014",
      "2022",
      "2021",
      "2023",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2022"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which date was the PM Internship Scheme launched?",
    "options": [
      "September 15, 2024",
      "October 3, 2024",
      "November 10, 2024",
      "January 9, 2025",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country's mission successfully demonstrated artificial photosynthesis in space?",
    "options": [
      "United States - Artemis",
      "Russia - Soyuz MS",
      "China - Shenzhou-19",
      "India - Gaganyaan",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How much funding has been allocated for the Samudrayaan Mission in the Union Budget?",
    "options": [
      "400 crore",
      "500 crore",
      "600 crore",
      "750 crore",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "600 crore"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country will host the BRICS Youth Council Entrepreneurship Working Group Meeting in March 2025?",
    "options": [
      "China",
      "Brazil",
      "India",
      "South Africa",
      "Russia"
    ],
    "answer": "India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as the Additional Director General, Directorate General of Foreign Trade (DGFT), as of February 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Anant Swarup",
      "Samar Nanda",
      "Santosh Kumar Verma",
      "Abhinav Gupta",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Marcus Stoinis, who recently announced his retirement from ODIs ahead of the Champions Trophy, represents which country in international cricket?",
    "options": [
      "England",
      "Australia",
      "South Africa",
      "New Zealand",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been awarded the Sahitya Akademi Award 2024 in Dogri literature?",
    "options": [
      "Jitendra Udhampuri",
      "Chaman Arora",
      "Veena Gupta",
      "Sushma Rani",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following groups of sites were newly added as Ramsar sites in India, bringing the total to 89?",
    "options": [
      "Sakkarakottai and Therthangal Bird Sanctuaries (Tamil Nadu), Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
      "Harike Wetland (Punjab), Chilika Lake (Odisha), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
      "Chilika Lake (Odisha), Loktak Lake (Manipur), and Sambhar Salt Lake (Rajasthan)",
      "Only Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim) and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Sakkarakottai and Therthangal Bird Sanctuaries (Tamil Nadu), Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of NASA's new space telescope set to launch in February 2025, which aims to survey the entire sky in 102 infrared colors?",
    "options": [
      "SPHEREx",
      "James Webb Space Telescope 2.0",
      "Hubble Space Telescope 2.0",
      "Chandra-CRISP X-ray Observatory",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "SPHEREx"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country recently passed strict hate crime laws, imposing a minimum 12-month jail term for public Nazi salutes and up to six years for terror-related hate crimes?",
    "options": [
      "Canada",
      "Australia",
      "Germany",
      "United Kingdom",
      "Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  }
]